Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the cryptoverse.
Today, we're going to talk about Bitcoin
as it wrestles with the 50-week moving
average. If you guys like the content,
make sure you subscribe to the channel,
give the video a thumbs up, and check
out the sale on Into the Cryptoverse
Premium at intothecryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, make sure to get your
ticket for the first ITC conference
that'll be coming up uh
in November, but if you want to get your
ticket before the prices go up, make
sure you do so before September 1st.
Link is in the description below.
Let's go ahead and jump in. So, Bitcoin
has I mean, last week it rallied about
24%.
This week, we've already seen Bitcoin
rally up to the 50-week moving average.
And, you know, I've had a lot of people
reach out and ask if this changes
anything.
Uh you know, could is it possible that
the bear market is it is over?
Um and so, I just want to sort of talk
through some of that stuff.
First of all, anything is always
possible, right? Four-year cycles
historically dictate that the low occurs
approximately
every 4 years. If you look at the S&P
500, it's approximately every every 4
years or so that you'll have major lows
in the market, and even going back to
the 1950s, '60s, and '70s, while often
times the low would occur later in the
year, like September or October. So,
October of of '66 and October of '74,
occasionally you will see the market
bottom out sooner, such as in the
summer. So, it it's not like it's
impossible, all right?
But, be that as it may, with you know,
with Bitcoin, one of the things I think
we should sort of consider here is what
historically has marked the end of the
bear market. Because it really depends
on which indicators you want to use. If
you want to use things like the MVRV
Z-score or
um you know, the balance price, the
realized price, you would argue for
lower prices. If you want to use things
like the supply of of Bitcoin in profit
or loss, which is a chart that we've
covered. If you want to use things like
time-based capitulation or other things
of that nature, it could suggest that it
it would take a little bit longer. As I
have said, and I publicly said on July
1st that the second half of midterm
years historically is the accumulation
window. It's hard to nail down the exact
low. What's interesting is that so far
that low occurred so far on July 1st,
the very first day of the second half of
the midterm year.
But,
if you guys remember when the bull
market was still, you know, back in
2025, when it first really started to
look like we were entering into the bear
market, what I said back then
that, you know, we thought it was a bear
market already, but then the final nail
in the coffin
for the bull market was the weekly close
below the 50-week moving average. If you
go back and look throughout all prior
bull markets, once you're below the
50-week moving average,
it's over, right? Like it it's always
been over when Bitcoin dropped below the
50-week. The bull market has always been
over. No matter how much people tried to
manifest the bull market back, it was
always over on weekly closes, on two
weekly closes below the 50-week moving
average. Now, if you zoom in
to 2022, you can find a week or two
where, you know, you you were
technically above it, but that's why I
say look for follow-through. It it's not
just the weekly close, it's the
follow-through beyond it. So, let me
show you some examples. In 2023,
when we got above the 50-week moving
average, it was a massive move up,
right? I mean, well above it, leaving no
doubt. In 2019,
when we got above it, there was
follow-through the next week, kind of
confirming that the bear market was
over. So, you can see two clear examples
right there of the bear market ending
when Bitcoin got through the 50-week
moving average. You can see that both
times it got to the 50-week though, it
hesitated for a little bit before
breaking through.
Now, if you go back uh even further to
2015, you can see that we got through
the 50-week moving average in October,
and there was follow-through the
following week. So, when you get through
it, if there's follow-through the next
week, that more or less confirms that
the bear market is in fact likely over.
Now, there are times, if you look at the
bull market support band, or in the case
of a bear market, the bear market
resistance band, there are plenty of
times where Bitcoin has broken through
the bear market resistance band, and
then got rejected at the 50-week moving
average. You can see that it happened in
April of 2022. You can see that it also
happened in July of 2018, right? So,
July 2018, we broke through the bull
market support band, wicked above the
50-week moving average, and then got
rejected, and then we came right back
down.
And then of course as well, in in 2015,
you can see that we got through the bull
market support band up to the 50-week,
got rejected, came back down, and then
on the next attempt, we were we were
successful. So, obviously, we all have
our bias as to what we want to happen,
right? I mean, it depends on whether
you've been DCA'ing, whether you
haven't. If you think the low's already
in, obviously you want the market to go
up. If you think the low is going to
come in Q4, you obviously want the
market to go down.
Clearly, I've been more so a pro
proponent of time-based capitulation,
where it can take the better part of a
year in order to really get the bull
market going again. That's at least what
history has shown us with the exception
of 2019, which if we're being honest,
there's there's some reasons to make
that comparison. As we've said, I mean,
we were one of the first channels
talking about this many, many years ago.
The comparison to the 2019 bull market
and how it was more or less a Bitcoin
dominance bull market
and why there would be no rotation into
altcoins. But, in this case,
we can all have our bias.
There's always what we want to happen.
What I'll say is this,
in the same way that
closes below the 50-week moving average
marked definitively that the bull market
was over,
I would argue that multiple closes above
the 50-week moving average, especially
with follow-through,
would probably, I mean, there's no such
thing as a sure thing, but would likely
dictate the the bear market being over
if Bitcoin can get above those levels.
All right?
Now, again, I know there's a lot of
emotions running right now and and
people want to know what's going to
happen, but I will say this, right? If
at any point you feel absolutely
convinced, beyond a shadow of a doubt,
that the low is in,
then
you know, not buying because you're up
20%, 30%, whatever off the low,
um it'd be like not buying Bitcoin at
20K in January 2023 because you didn't
buy the bottom or not buying Bitcoin at
$5,000 in April 2019 because you missed
the low. Right? Like, at the time, it
can feel bad to buy, but it's not
necessarily about time, obviously, if
the low is in. And so, this is why a lot
of people want to know if the low is in
is because if it is, they don't want to
get left behind, but at the same time,
they don't want to be be schmuck FOMOing
in at a local high. And this is why I I
pleaded with people for the last couple
of months that
talking about new lows is more of an
academic exercise and that I was still
DCAing
in the second half of the midterm year
below 0.3 risk, which unfortunately only
occurred for 5 days, right? 5 days.
So,
not a very long period of time.
Admittedly, you know, I I
arguably starting to buy on July 1st
wasn't the worst day to buy because that
actually marked the low.
Uh but now there's all these narratives
swirling on Twitter
uh from you know, especially from people
that were were bull posting the entire
way down that are you know, hell-bent on
on creating their own narratives. But
again,
you got to let that stuff go, right?
Like I can't listen to all that stuff.
All I have to listen to is the chart.
That's all I have. Like I don't care
about the opinions of you know, of of
the people that just want to
create drama for the sake of creating
drama. What I want to do
is I want to listen
to what the chart is saying, right? And
if there is acceptance
above the 50-week,
I will listen to that. And I will not,
you know, bang the drum that it has to
play out a different way.
But at the same time, I have to look
through history and say, "Look, there
have also been times where Bitcoin
rallied through the bear market
resistance band only to get rejected by
the 50-week." It happened in the summer
of 2018. It happened in 2015. It also
happened in 2022.
You could also argue that every cycle
Bitcoin gets rejected by the 50-week
moving average at some point, right? You
can see in 2018 it happened in in July
in 2014.
Um Um it didn't happen until the
post-halving year, but still rejected by
it on the first attempt, okay?
And to a new low, it happened in 2022,
rejected by the 50-week.
We haven't actually made it to the
50-week yet. Like we got close back in
January when Bitcoin rallied up to
almost 98k, but at the time the 50-week
moving average
was closer to like what? 100k?
Yeah, it was it was 101k at the time.
So, really this is Bitcoin's first time
even testing the 50-week moving average
throughout the bear market. And again,
this is something that has always been
tested in all prior bear markets was the
50-week moving average. And so now the
question just simply becomes do we
accept above it or below it?
Time-based capitulation would suggest it
it's going to be hard to get through.
Okay? If I were to just look at
time-based capitulation and the way the
market historically acts, it would argue
that it's a little too early to get
through it.
Be that as it may.
If the market proves me wrong
and says, "You know what? Great idea,
Ben,
but you're wrong."
Then I will accept that and I I will
come on here
as clear as I am now and say, "Look,
the the bear market at that point would
be over in my opinion. In my opinion."
But until that time occurs, right? Until
that time occurs,
I feel like I would do I'd be doing
myself a disservice to ignore, you know,
some of the prior moves above the bear
market resistance band that led us to
the 50-week only to be rejected.
So, let's see what happens. If it's a
rejection by the 50-week, it should
happen sooner rather than later, right?
I don't think we would linger for too
long if it's going to be a rejection.
The longer we stay at elevated prices,
you would argue the more likely it is
that we would break through. Like in
2018 when we got up to the 50-week
moving average, we got up to it one week
and then the next week we were rejected.
In 2015 when we got up to it, we got up
to it and then the next week we were
just rejected back down and then we got
back up to it once more, but again, it
was the second week.
A clear rejection off the 50-week moving
average after getting to it. So, next
week will be instrumental in helping us
understand
is this just simply a rally to a
rejection or is it more? Because if it's
more than what you would expect, you
would expect to linger at the 50-week
for a number of weeks and then to break
through. Maybe find support at the bull
market support band and then break
through.
Those are my thoughts. I'm trying to be
as honest as I can. I'm trying to
communicate as clearly as I can. I know
emotions are running hot right now,
running really, really high. Uh but
those are my views. Thank you guys for
tuning in.
Make sure you subscribe, give the video
thumbs up, and hopefully I'll see you at
the conference in November. Link's in
the description below. I'll see you guys
next time. Bye.